Zishi (Violet) Wu ziwu@ucdavis.edu Jan.25, 2021

Dear Professor Karp and Ms. Lauck,

I am writing to apply for the field technician position with the Nestbox Project. I am currently a junior undergraduate student at UC Davis, pursuing a bachelor's degree in Wildlife, Fish, and Conservation Biology with a minor in Forensic Entomology. I am in Professor Karp's Conservation Ecology course this quarter, so I got to know this opportunity. My career goal is to become an ecology researcher focusing on bird conservation, and I really want to seize this great opportunity to gain hands-on experience working with songbirds.

I've been birding for only over a year, but I am now an active birder and am confident in bird identification in California, especially around Davis and along Putah creek. I participated in three Christmas bird counts this year in Putah Creek, Sacramento, and Rio Cosumnes. The more I learn about birds in the wild, through photography, in literature, or in classes, the more eager I am to seek opportunities that allow me to contribute to conserving them better. As a volunteer in the California Raptor Center, I have experience handling, netting, and releasing raptors. I know every bird well with their names, stories, and little habits when stepping on a trainer's glove, and I absolutely love working with them. Doing health examinations and preparing them medicines let me develop an awareness of following protocols well with attention to detail. In addition, I am gentle and patient when handling live creatures. I found these traits useful when working with insect specimens or live caterpillars in our lab. I am also very fond of working in the field. I gained experience in field data collection and teamwork from a course offered by the University of California Natural Reserves, California Ecology and Conservation, in which we spent a winter camping in remote natural areas for intensive training in experimental design, data collection, and scientific writing. Vigorous birding trips have also prepared me well for long-distance hiking in rugged areas. I believe these traits and experiences made me a good candidate for this project. I am also longing to learn bird banding for a long time! I really hope to get involved in bird surveys or monitoring instead of just observing and taking pictures of them in the wild.

My spring and summer schedule is flexible, and I have attached my resume. I look forward to discussing my qualifications with you. Thank you for your time and consideration!

Sincerely, Violet Wu

# Zishi (Violet) Wu

Davis, CA 95618 | (530) 601-3992

Email: ziwu@ucdavis.edu

### **EDUCATION**

Bachelor of Science in Wildlife, Fish, and Conservation Biology, minor in Forensic Entomology

University of California, Davis Expected graduation: June 2023

Current GPA:3.961

Related Courses: Biol Cons Wild Birds, Intro to Ecology, Wildlife Ecology, Conservation Biology

# **SKILLS**

Bird Identification Animal Handling Field data collection

#### **EXPERIENCE**

**Undergraduate Researcher**, Yang Lab (Davis, CA)

June 2021- Present

- Monitor milkweed growth in the field, collect and input data for a long-termed ecology study.
- Independent research on the impact of temperature-derived melanization on monarch caterpillars.

#### Content Creator, Bilibili (Remote)

March 2021-Present

- Film, edit, and narrate wildlife documentaries and educational videos about insect physiology and ecology.
- 106 thousand subscribers and 3.6 million views in <u>my channel</u> up to date.

**Volunteer**, California Raptor Center (Davis, CA)

June 2021-Present

• Responsible for feeding, cleaning, handling, health examination, public education, and some medical treatment for the birds.

#### **Academic Associate,** Easy group Inc (Remote)

June 2020- September 2021

• Tutor higher level IB (International baccalaureate) Biology. Content includes cell biology, plant and animal physiology, genetics, and ecology.

Research Intern, Primate Social Behavior and Conservation Project (Davis, CA) March 2021- August 2021

• Read and code research articles on chimpanzee cognition using Primate Cognition Test Battery Analysis.

### Research Intern, UC Davis Dairy (Davis, CA)

October 2020- January 2021

- Assist research conducted by PhD student studying ruminant metabolism and animal nutrition.
- Help in husbandry and treatment of 20 dairy cattle in a feed additive trial. Work includes feeding, cleaning, and collecting milk data.

#### FIELDWORK EXPERIENCE

**Student,** California Ecology and Conservation Program (San Bernardino, CA) *January 2021-March*2021

- Design and conducted scientific research while camping in remote natural field over 50 days.
- Analyze data, present, and publish research results.

#### **PUBLICATION**

Jacob, F., Lucy, M., Roxana, R., **Zishi, W.** 2021. "Evidence of niche partitioning among small mammals in the Eastern Mojave Desert from scat distribution" *CEC Research* Vol. 5 Issue 2. doi.org/10.21973/N3G660.

# **AWARDS**

Tracy and Ruth Storer Scholarship	2021-2022
Elizabeth Graves Hosselkus Scholarship	2020-2021
Robert B. Wilson Scholarship	2020-2021
Gail E. and Ruth M. Oliver Scholarship	2019-2020
Dean's list, Collage of Agriculture and Environmental Sciences	2019-2021

# **ACTIVITIES**

• Member, UC Davis Birdwatching Club

September 2021 - Present

• Member, UC Davis Woman's Ultimate Frisbee B team

September 2019 - September 2021

• Member, Beijing National Day School musical cast crew

February 2018- June 2019

• Participant, iGEM (International Genetic Engineered Machine) competition high school division

December 2017-December 2018